神秘博士50週年特別奉獻
"不要浪費時間討論好人的標準
"Waste no more time arguing about what a good man should be
成為他" --馬可·奧勒留
Be one" Marcus Aurelius
你跑著來的?
Have you been running?
你沒事吧? 有你的電話 在辦公室
Are you OK? There was a call for you, at the office
你的醫生(doctor)打來的
From your doctor
他留下地址了嗎?
Did he leave an address?
高等量子力學
過堂風!
Draught!
想不想去古美索不達米亞待一周
Fancy a week in Ancient Mesopotamia
然後去未來的火星?
followed by future Mars?
有雞尾酒嗎?
Will there be cocktails?
月亮上有
On the moon
有就去!
The moon'll do!
新工作怎麼樣? 教了什麼?
Hows the new job? Teach anything good?
沒有 學到什麼沒?
No Learn anything?
沒有
Not a thing
- 發生了什麼?
- 我們起飛了
- Whats happening?
- Whoa, whoa Were taking off
但引擎沒還沒發動!
But the engines arent going!
風車11號呼叫灰狗領袖
Windmill 11 to Greyhound Leader
藍鷹已升空 準備接收
Blue Eagle is airborne Ready to receive
我們已出發
Were on our way
你好 Kate Stewart的電話
Hello, Kate Stewarts phone?
哦 稍等
Oh, hold on
抱歉 對不起!
Excuse mesorry!
長官!長官!
Maam! Maam!
渡鴉看上去有些無精打采
The ravens are looking a bit sluggish
- 告訴Malcolm它們需要新電池
- 是他!
- Tell Malcolm they need new batteries
- Its him!
抱歉 是你的私人電話 但是
Sorry, its your personal phone,but, well
我認得這個鈴聲 是他 對嗎?
I recognised the ringtone Its him, isnt it?
哮喘伴侶
Inhaler
博士 你好 我們在野外發現了TARDIS
Doctor, helloWe found the TARDIS in a field
- 我正讓他們運過來
- 你真是沒開玩笑！
- Im having it brought in
- No kidding!
你在哪兒?
Where are you?
天啊!
Oh, my God!
博士 我很抱歉 我們不知道你還在裡面
Oh, Doctor, Im so sorry, we had no idea you were still in there
快來
Come on
收到 新目的地 - 207 改變航線
Roger New heading - 207 Changing course
- 博士?!
- Clara!
- Doctor?!
博士 能聽到嗎?
Doctor, can you hear me?
- 他大概聽不到
- 下次
- I dont think he can hear me
- Next time
先敲門會死嗎?
would it kill you to knock?
我把你直接送到現場
Im having you taken directly to the scene
博士 你沒事吧?
Doctor, hello, are you OK?
等會再聊
Whoa!Im just going to pop you on hold
- 博士?
- 博士!
- Doctor?
- Ah! Doctor!
立正!
Attention!
我為什麼敬禮?
Why am I saluting?
博士 作為首席科學家
Doctor, as Chief Scientific Officer,
請允許我轉達UNIT的正式道歉
may I extend the official apologies of UNIT?
Kate Lethbridge-Stewart 給你個建議
Kate Lethbridge-Stewart, a word to the wise
我肯定你父親也會告訴你
As Im sure your father wouldve told you,
我不喜歡被撿（有勾搭之意）
I dont like being picked up
可能在他腦子裡聽上去更好一點
That probably sounded better in his head
我是按君主的命令行事
Im acting on instructions direct from the throne
伊麗莎白一世女王陛下的密令
Sealed orders from Her Majesty,Queen Elizabeth the First
女王? 一世? 抱歉 伊麗莎白一世?
The Queen? The First? Sorry, Elizabeth the First?
她的信物在裡面
Her credentials are inside
不 在裡面
No Inside
圍巾不錯
Nice scarf
對外怎麼解釋?
Whats our cover story for this?
- Derren Brown的魔術
- 又這個?
- Um, Derren Brown
- Again?
我們已經給他送了花
Oh, weve sent him flowers
立正!
Attention!
封鎖畫廊周圍
Right, I want a secure perimeter around the gallery
你認識她? 伊麗莎白一世?
Did you know her? Elizabeth the First?
- 聯合情報特派組
- 什麼?
- Unified Intelligence Task Force
- Sorry?
這些人 UNIT 他們調查外星事物 任何外星的東西
This lot UNIT They investigate
alien stuff, anything alien
- 什麼 就像你?
- 我為他們工作
- What, like you?
- I work for them
- 你有工作?!
- 我為什麼不能有工作?
- You have a job?!
- Why shouldnt I have a job?
我很擅長有工作
Id be brilliant at having a job
你不可能有工作!
You dont have a job!
我有 這就是我的工作 我正在做
I do This is my job,I'm doing it now
- 你從沒有過工作
- 我有!我有
- You never have a job
- I do! I do
伊麗莎白女王的信物 博士
Elizabeths credentials, Doctor
但
But
但這不可能
but thats not possible
終結
No more
- 這是標題
- 我知道標題!
- Thats the title
- I know the title!
也名為Gallifrey的隕落
Also known as Gallifrey Falls
這副畫不屬於這裡
This painting doesnt belong here
- 不是這個時間和地點
- 顯然
- not in this time or place
- Obviously
這是Arcadia的陷落
Its the fall of Arcadia
Gallifrey第二大城市
Gallifreys second city
但它是怎麼做到的? 這怎麼可能?
But how is it doing that? How is that possible?
這是油畫
Its an oil painting
是3D的
in 3D
時間領主藝術
Time Lord art
裡面比外面大 一小段真實時間
Bigger on the inside A slice of real time
被凍結
frozen
伊麗莎白女王告訴了我們去哪兒找和它的重要性
Elizabeth told us where to find itand its significance
你沒事吧?
You OK?
他在那兒
He was there
- 誰?
- 我
- Who was?
- Me
另一個我
The other me
我從不談論的那個
The one I dont talk about
我不明白
I dont understand
我有過很多張面孔 很多次生命
Ive had many faces, many lives
不是每一個我都認可
I dont admit to all of them
有一段生命我一直努力忘記
Theres one life Ive tried very hard to forget
終結
No more
他參加了時間之戰
He was the Doctor who fought in the Time War
就是那天他做了那件事 我做了那件事
and that was the day he did it - the day I did it
那天他殺死了所有人
The day he killed them all
時間之間的最後一天
The last day of the Time War
那場結束我們和Dalek之間所有戰爭的戰役
The war to end all wars between my people and the Daleks
在那場戰役中有一個人手上沾染的鮮血
And in that battle, there was a man with more blood on his hands
比任何人都多
than any other
一個人犯下了全宇宙聞之噤聲的罪行
A man who would commit a crime that would silence the universe
那個人就是 我
and that man was me
消滅!
Exterminate!
給最高議會的信息 優先級: 緊急
Message for the High Council,Priority Omega
Arcadia被攻陷了 再說一次 Arcadia被攻陷了
Arcadia has fallenI repeat, Arcadia has fallen
士兵
Soldier
我需要你的槍
Im going to need your gun
消滅!
Exterminate!
不要!求求你 不要!
Please! Please, just dont!
警報!警報!
Alert! Alert!
發現博士!
The Doctor is detected!
博士已被包圍!
The Doctor is surrounded!
通知最高指揮 我們找到博士了!
Inform High Command,we have the Doctor!
尋找 定位 摧毀!
Seek, locate, destroy!
博士已被包圍
The Doctor is surrounded
尋找 定位 摧毀! 尋找
Seek, locate, destroy! Seek
博士已逃跑
The Doctor is escaping
這是什麼字?
What are these words?
解釋!
Explain!
最高議會在召開緊急會議
The High Council is in emergency session
- 他們有自己的計劃
- 去他的最高議會
- they have plans of their own
- To hell with the High Council
他們的計劃早就失敗了
their plans have already failed
Gallifrey仍然岌岌可危
Gallifreys still in the line of fire
他在那兒 然後呢?
So he was there, then?
他留下了一條給Dalek的文字警告
He left a message,a written warning for the Daleks
他是個蠢貨
Hes a fool
不 他是個瘋子
No Hes a madman
你看 長官 星球周圍所有的Dalek艦隊
As you can see, sir, all Dalek fleets surrounding the planet
現在都匯聚到了首都 但天溝戰壕還能堅持
now converging on the capital,but the Sky Trenches are holding
他接下來去了哪兒?
Where did he go next?
這重要嗎? 這是他們最猛烈的進攻 長官
What does it matter? This is their biggest ever attack, sir
- 他們向我們全力開火了
- 長官
- theyre throwing everything at us
- Sir
時間之庫被人侵入了
we have a security breach to the Time Vaults
終極武器庫
The Omega Arsenal
所有被禁用的武器都封存在那兒
where all the forbidden weapons are locked away
它們不再是被禁用的了
Theyre not forbidden any more
已經全部被用來對付Dalek
weve used them all against the Daleks
不
No
不 不是全部
No, we havent
時間之匣不見了
The Moment is gone
我不明白 時間之匣是什麼? 我從沒聽說過
I dont understand What is the Moment? Ive never heard of it
星際噬者
The galaxy eater
Gallifrey先民的終極作品
The final work of the ancients of Gallifrey
非常強大的武器 強大到它的操作系統發展出了感知能力
a weapon so powerful, the operating system became sentient
根據傳說
According to legend
它擁有了意識
it developed a conscience
我們從沒用過?
And weve never used it?
你要怎麼使用一件能對你做出評判的
How do you use a weapon of ultimate mass destruction
終極大規模殺傷性武器?
when it can stand in judgment on you?
只有一個人會嘗試
There is only one man who would even try
Gallifrey之時間領主 Skaro之Dalek
Time Lords of Gallifrey, Daleks of Skaro
這是給你們所有人的通知
I serve notice on you all
我已經等待了太久 這一切必須結束
Too long I have stayed my hand
No more
今天 你們讓我別無選擇
Today, you leave me no choice
今天 這場戰爭終將結束
Today, this war will end
終結
No more
怎麼
How
怎麼操作?
how do you work?
為什麼就不能有個大紅按鈕?
Why is there never a big red button?
你好?
Hello?
有人嗎?
Is somebody there?
什麼也不是
Its nothing
只是匹狼
Its just a wolf
- 別坐那上面!
- 為什麼不行?
- Dont sit on that!
- Why not?
因為那不是椅子
Because its not a chair
它是宇宙中最危險的武器
its the most dangerous weapon in the universe
怎麼不能也是椅子呢?
Why cant it be both?
你為什麼停在那麼遠的地方?
Why did you park so far away?
你不想讓她見到嗎?
Didnt you want her to see it?
讓誰?
Want who to see?
TARDIS
The TARDIS
你走了很遠
You walked for miles
很遠 很遠 很遠
And miles and miles and miles and miles
- 我在思考!
- 我聽到了
- I was thinking!
- I heard you
你聽到了?
You heard me?
終結
No more
- 終結! 終結!
- 停下
- No more! No more!
- Stop it!
- 終結
- 你是誰?
- No more
- Who are you?
它啟動了! 快離開這兒!
Its activating Get out of here!
怎麼了?
Whats wrong?
操作界面很燙
The interface is hot
好吧 我盡力了
Well, I do my best
裡面有個能量源
Theres a power source inside
你就是操作界面?
Youre the Interface?
他們肯定告訴過你時間之匣有意識
They must have told you the Moment had a conscience
你好!
Hello!
看看你
Oh, look at you
被困在一個女孩和一個盒子之間
Stuck between a girl and a box
一生都這樣吧 博士?
Story of your life, eh, Doctor?
你認識我?
You know me?
我聽到你
I hear you
每一代的你 在你們那個又老又破的腦袋裡吵吵嚷嚷
All of you, jangling around in that dusty old head of yours
我特別為你選了這張臉和這個形態
I chose this face and form especially for you
它來自你的過去
Its from your past
或是你的未來 我總是把這兩個搞混
Or possibly your future - I always get those two mixed up
我沒有未來
I don't have a future
我想我叫
I think I'm called
Rose Tyler
哦 不對 等下 抱歉
No, yes, no, sorry
不不不 在這個形態 我叫
No, no, in this form Im called
惡狼
Bad Wolf
你怕大惡狼嗎 博士?
Are you afraid of the big bad wolf, Doctor?
- 別再叫我博士了
- 你自己的意識裡就是這麼叫的
- Stop calling me Doctor
- Thats the name in your head
不應該是這樣的
It shouldnt be
這場戰爭我已經打了很久
Ive been fighting this war for a very long time
我已經失去了被叫做博士的資格
Ive lost the right to be the Doctor
那麼你就是傳說中救了我們所有人的那個
Then youre the one to save us all
是的
Yes
如果我能發展出自負 那就是你了
If I ever develop an ego,youve got the job
如果你曾經和我心靈相通
If you have been inside my head
那麼你就該知道我目睹過的一切
then you know what Ive seen
我所經歷的痛苦
The suffering
時間和空間的每一寸都在燃燒
Every moment in time and space is burning
這一切必須結束
It must end
我將以我唯一能做到的方式終結它
And I intend to end it the only way I can
而你就用我來終結它? 把時間領主和Dalek
And youre going to use me to end it by killing them all
全都殺死?
Daleks and Time Lords alike
我可以 但是你得承擔後果
I could, but there will be consequences for you
我本就抱著必死之心
I have no desire to survive this
那麼這就是對你的懲罰
Then thats your punishment
如果你這麼做了--把他們都殺了-- 這就是所謂的後果
If you do this - if you kill them all
- then thats the consequence
你會活下去
You live
Gallifrey
你會燒掉Gallifrey
youre going to burn it
連同所有的Dalek 但也包括所有的孩子
and all those Daleks with it
but all those children too
Gallifrey上有多少孩子?
How many children on Gallifrey right now?
我不知道
I dont know
總有一天你會計數你殺死了多少孩子
One day you will count them
在一個可怕的夜晚
One terrible night
你想知道你會變成什麼嗎
Do you want to see
what that will turn you into?
別裝了! 難道你不好奇嗎
Come on! Arent you curious?
我可以為你開啟通向你的未來的窗口
Im opening windows on your future
穿過紛亂糾纏的未來
A tangle in time through the days to come
找到今日過後你將成為的人
to the man today will make of you
好吧 沒想到會變這樣子
OK, I wasnt expecting that
但是時間之戰已經結束
But the Time Wars over
你幹嘛把我們帶來看一幅畫?
Why have you brought us here to look at a painting?
這幅畫只是伊麗莎白的信物
The painting only serves as Elizabeths credentials
來證明那封信是她寫的
proof that the letter is from her
這不是你來這的真正原因
Its not why youre here
吾愛 我希望這幅名叫"Gallifrey的隕落"的畫作
My dearest love, I hope the painting known as Gallifrey Falls
可以證明這封信出自你的伊麗莎白之手
will serve as proof that it is your Elizabeth who writes to you now
你將會想起你曾發誓
You will recall that you pledged yourself
捍衛我的王國
to the safety of my kingdom
既然如此 我任命你為這間地下藝術館的館長
In this capacity,I have appointed you as curator
這裡封存著對英格蘭的致命威脅
of the Under Gallery where deadly danger to England is locked away
如若館內發生任何變故
Should any disturbance occur within its walls
我願你能聽到召喚 上帝保佑你,夫君
it is my wish that you be summoned God speed, gentle husband
發生了什麼
What happened?
你看看就知道了
Easier to show you
McGillop
不可能啊 我剛剛才
But thats not possible I was just
明白 長官 但是 為什麼我要把它帶到那裡?
Understood, sir But why would I take it there?
伊麗莎白一世? 你認識她?
Elizabeth the First? You knew her, then?
很久之前
A long time ago
Allons-y!
這下你懂了吧 女王陛下 早跟你說了吧
There you go, Your Majesty,what did I tell you?
裡面比外面大!
Bigger on the inside!
門可不是 差點把我的頭削掉
The door isnt - you nearly took my head off
平時都是我削別人的
Its normally me who does that
告訴我,博士 為什麼我要在你身上浪費時間
我還有戰爭要準備
Tell me, Doctor, why Im wasting my time on you I have wars to plan
我們有野餐之約啊
You have a picnic to eat
你可以幫我的
You could help me
我在幫你享受野餐啊
Im helping you eat the picnic
但是你有征戰的野心
But you have a stomach for war
這張臉經歷過了戰火
This face has seen conflict
太明顯了
its clear as day
你不會相信我所經歷過的戰爭
Oh, Ive seen conflict
like you wouldnt believe
不過不是這張臉
But it wasnt this face
不說這個了 陛下 快站起來 起來!
But never mind that, Your Majesty -
up on your feet! Up, up!
你怎麼敢!
How dare you?!
我可是英格蘭的女王!
Im the Queen of England!
我可不是英格蘭人
Im not English
伊麗莎白
Elizabeth
你願意嫁給我嗎
will you marry me?
哦吾愛 親愛的 我當然願意!
Oh, my dear, sweet love
Of course I will!
- 啊哈 露陷了吧!
- 吾愛?
- Ah! Gotcha!
- My love?
第一!真正的伊麗莎白絕對不會接受我的求婚
One! The real Elizabeth would never
have accepted my marriage proposal
第二!真正的伊麗莎白會懷疑
Two! The real Elizabeth would notice
當我提及我有不同的面孔
when I just casually mention
having a different face
最後!真正的伊麗莎白
But then the real Elizabeth
不是一個來自異星的變形生物!
isnt an alien shape-shifting
from outer space!
並且
And
叮!
ding
那是什麼?
Whats that?
這是一個專門會丁丁響的機器
Its a machine that goes ding!
叮!我自己做的
DING! Made it myself
檢測到變形生物DNA時會發光
It lights up in the presence
of shape-shifter DNA Ooh
還能加熱20英尺外冷掉的晚餐
Also it can microwave
frozen dinners from up to 20 feet
還可以從未來下載漫畫
and download comics from the future
唉我真是太有才了
I never know when to stop
吾愛 我聽不懂你說的
My love, I do not understand
我可不是你的愛人 而且你明明知道我在說什麼
Im not your love
And yes, you do!
你可是一個Zygon
Youre a Zygon
我是Zygon?
A Zygon?
別裝了 我都揭穿你了
對啊 你就是Zygon
Oh, stop it, its over!
A Zygon, yes
一坨紅色佈滿吸盤的橡膠泥
A big red rubbery thing,
covered in suckers
不過吻技不錯
Surprisingly good kisser
你以為真正的英格蘭女王會決定
Think the real Queen of England
would just decide
和穿著合身西裝的英俊男子分享王權?
to share the throne with any old
handsome bloke in a tight suit
就因為他有完美的頭髮
just cos hes got amazing hair
和一匹駿馬?
and a nice horse?
是那匹馬!
It was the horse!
我要當國王了!
I'm going to be King!
- 快跑!
- 發生了什麼!
- 我們被來自異星的變形生物
- Run! -Whats happening?
- Were being attacked
攻擊了!
by a shape-shifting alien
from outer space
- 他之前偽裝成了我的馬
- 你到底在說什麼?
- formerly disguised as my horse
- What does that mean?
這意味著 我們需要一匹新馬了
It means
were going to need a new horse
它要去哪?
Wheres it going?
我去拖住他 你先跑
Ill hold it off, you run
你的子民需要你
Your people need you
我還需要你活著來參加我們的婚禮
And I need you
alive for our wedding day
哈! 幹得好啊博士! 吻得不錯!
Oh, good work, Doctor, nice one!
童貞女王? 已經是歷史啦！
The Virgin Queen? So much for history!
出來啊!
Come on!
我知道你在這
Know youre there!
DING!
SHE PANTS
SHE SCREAMS
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa
哈 以為偽裝成兔子我就不知道嗎
Oh, very clever
不論你的陰謀是什麼 快點放棄吧
Whatever youve got planned,
forget it
我是博士
Im the Doctor
我已經活了904年了
Im 904 years old
我來自Kasterborous星座的Gallifrey
Im from the planet Gallifrey in
the constellation of Kasterborous
我是暴風之王黑暗之君
I am the oncoming storm,
the bringer of darkness,
而你...就是一隻小兔子對吧?
and you are basically
just a rabbit, arent you?
好吧 不說了
OK, carry on -
給你一個普通的
just ageneral
警告罷了
warning
博士!
Doctor!
伊麗莎白！
Elizabeth!
那到底是什麼!告訴我!
That thing explain what it is!
它到底想要什麼?
What does it want of us?
這也是我疑惑的
Thats what Im trying to find out
應該也就是你們的星球吧
Probably just your planet
博士?
快離開她 博士
Step away from her, Doctor
那不是我 是那個怪物
Thats not me, thats the creature
這怎麼可能? 她長得跟我一模一樣
How is that possible? Shes me
博士 她跟我一模一樣!
Doctor, shes me!
我本來就是我 別把誇我的當成誇你的
I am, indeed, me A compliment
that cannot be extended to yourself
不可思議!
Extraordinary!
這個怪物跟我一模一樣
The creature has captured
my exact likeness -
不可思議
this is exceptional
不可思議? 女王會認為這是無禮
Exceptional? A Queen
would call it impertinent
女王會感到必須先欣賞
A Queen would feel
compelled to admire
執行任務的能力
the skill of the execution -
再安排任務(死刑)
before arranging one
它不工作了!
Ah! Its not working!
可以想到這種生物很快就能讓自己
One might surmise
the creature would learn quickly
不被輕易的識別出
to protect itself
from any simple means of detection
顯然你更瞭解這種生物
Clearly you understand
the creature better than I
你更有優勢
But then you have the advantage
你們倆 都後退!
Back, both of you, now!
這是一個時間裂縫 現實的撕裂口
Thats a time fissure,
a tear in the fabric of reality
什麼都可能發生!
Anything could happen!
比如
For instance
一頂土耳其氈帽
a fez
這邊請
This way
歡迎來到地下藝術館
Welcome to the Under Gallery
這裡伊麗莎白一世用於保存
This is where Elizabeth the First
kept all art
所有被認定過於危險 不宜公開展示的藝術品之處
deemed too dangerous
for public consumption
石之塵
Stone dust
這很重要嗎?
Is it important?
我活了1200年 還從沒有踩到過不重要的東西
In 1,200 years, Ive never stepped
in anything that wasnt
嘿 說你呢!你懂科學嗎?
Oi, you! Are you sciencey?
噢 額 恩是的
Oh, erm Well, erm yes
有名字麼? 嗯
Got a name? Yes
好 我一直想遇見叫做「嗯」的人
Good, Ive always wanted to meet someone called Yes
現在 拿這些石塵去分析
Now, I want this stone dust analysed
然後給我報告 一式三份
And I want a report in triplicate,
裡面要有很多的圖表和複雜的函數公式
with lots of graphs and diagrams and complicated sums,
放我桌上 明天早上 盡快 立刻馬上 哈哈哈
on my desk, tomorrow morning, ASAP,pronto, LOL
瞧 工作
See? Job
我有桌子嗎 沒有 那我還要張桌子!
Do I have a desk? No And I want a desk!
組隊分析這些石塵
Get a team, analyse the stone dust
哮喘伴侶!
（SHE WHEEZES）Inhaler!
哪一天你才能走過土耳其氈帽而無動於衷
Someday,you could just walk past a fez
絕不可能
Never going to happen
遵照你的命令 什麼都沒被動過
As you instructed,nothing has been touched
這就是為什麼我們叫你來的原因
This is why we called you in
又是3D的
3D again
有趣 破了的玻璃?
InterestingThe broken glass?
不
No
它從哪裡被打碎
where its broken from
看看這碎片的形狀
Look at the shatter pattern
這些畫的玻璃都是從裡面被打碎的
The glass on all these paintings has been broken from the inside
正如你所看到 這些都是風景畫
As you can see,all the paintings are landscapes -
沒有任何人像 所以?
no figures of any kind So?
曾經有過
There used to be
有東西從畫裡溜了出來? 很多東西
Somethings got out of the paintings?Lots of somethings
危險
Dangerous
整個地方都被搜尋過
This whole place has been searched
沒有不該在的東西 也沒有丟失的物件
Theres nothing here that shouldnt be, and nothings got out
哦 不!不是現在!
Oh, no! Not now!
博士 那是什麼?不 不是現在 我忙著呢!
Doctor, what is it?No, not now - Im busy!
這跟這些畫有關係嗎?
Is it to do with the paintings?
不 不 完全無關 我還記得這個
No, no This is different I remember this
差不多還記得
Almost remember
哦 當然!
Oh, of course!
該我進去的時候來了
This is where I come in
Geronimo-o
博士!等等
Doctor! Wait
哦!
o-o-o!
呻吟
HE GROANS
這人是誰?
Who is this man?
我也在納悶這事
Thats just what I was wondering
哦 很瘦（受）唉
Oh, that is skinny
真的是很瘦
That is proper skinny
我還從沒從外面看過這身材
Ive never seen it from the outside
就像特效那樣 噢!哈!火柴棍兒!
Its like a special effect Oi! Ha! Matchstick man!
你該不會是
Youre not
掩蓋 掩蓋什麼?重生 本就像次抽獎
Compensating? For what? Regeneration - its a lottery
哦 他還真酷 不是麼?
Oh, hes cool Isnt he cool?
"我是博士 我哪裡都酷爆了 咦 我怎麼會穿著雙膠底鞋"
"Im the Doctor and Im all cool -oops, Im wearing sandshoes!"
你在這幹什麼?我忙著呢
What are you doing here? Im busy
哦 忙?唔 這就是我們稱之為忙的嗎 嗯?嗯?
Oh, busy? I see, is that what were calling it, eh? Eh?
女士們 你們好啊 別這樣 聽著
Hello, ladies Dont start Listen, what you get up to
你自己重生了之後搞什麼名堂是你的事兒
in the privacy of your own regeneration is your business
她們其中之一是Zygon
One of them is a Zygon
額
Urgh
我可沒在批評你
Im not judging you
WHOOSHING
哦 真可愛!
Oh, lovely!
女王陛下現在或許是逃走的好機會
Your Majestiesprobably a good time to run
-但那怪物怎麼辦? -伊麗莎白
But what about the creature? Elizabeth, whichever one of you
隨便你們哪個是真的 現在轉身往跟另一個相反的方向跑吧
is the real one, turn and run in the opposite direction to the other one
當然 吾愛!
BOTH: Of course, my love!
活下去 吾愛
Stay alive, my love
我和你可還沒完呢
I am not done with you yet
多謝啊 親愛的
Thanks Lovely
我理解 為我而活著 達令
I understandLive for me, my darling
我們很快又會在一起
We shall be together again
恩 這不是很好麼?
Well, wont that be nice?
她們其中之一是Zygon 恩
One of those was a Zygon Yeah
巨大的紅色橡膠怪物 上面滿是吸盤 唔
Big red rubbery thingCovered in suckers Yeah
舌頭上有毒液囊泡 夠 我知道你說啥了 謝了 好
Venom sacs in the tongue Yeah,Im getting the point, thanks Nice
博士?是你嗎?啊!你好啊Clara!你能聽見我嗎?
CLARA: Doctor? Is that you? Ah! Hello, Clara! Can you hear me?
恩 是我 我們能聽見你 你在哪?
Yeah, its me, we can hear youWhere are you?
我們在哪?英格蘭 1562年
Where are we?England 1562
你在跟誰說話?
Who are you talking to?
我自己
BOTH: Myself
你能回來嗎?
KATE: Can you come back through?
物理通道可能並不是雙向的
Physical passage may not be possible in both directions
它啊!
Its Ah!
等等!氈帽來啦!
Hang on! Fez incoming!
什麼都沒有唉
Nothing here
它去哪了?
So where did it go?
-他在跟誰說話? -他說了 他自己
CLARA: Whos he talking to?KATE: He said - himself
讓他一直說下去 Malcolm?
Keep him talking Malcolm? Malcolm,I need you to send me
Malcolm 我要你給我發一份我父親的案件檔案 編號克羅默（10週年的梗）
one of my fathers incident files -codenamed Cromer
70年代或者是80年代  取決於編製日期協議
70s or 80s, depending on the dating protocol
GURGLING
好 你曾經是我 你已經做過一次了接下來會發生些什麼?
OK, you used to be me, youve done all this before - what happens next?
我不記得了
I dont remember
你怎麼能忘記這?!
How can you forget this?!
嘿 等等 這可不是我的錯
Hey, hang on, its not MY fault
很明顯你沒有足夠重視問題 反轉極性!
Youre obviously not paying enough attention Reverse the polarity!
沒用唉 我倆都在反轉極性
Its not working Were both reversing the polarity!
對 我就知道 這裡有兩個我們 我在反轉它
Yes, I know that Theres two of us - Im reversing it,
你又把它轉回來 我們在逗這極場玩啊
and youre reversing it back again!Were confusing the polarity
誰丟了個氈帽?
Anyone lose a fez?
你
You
你怎麼會在這裡
How can you be here?
更確切的說 你為什麼在這裡
More to the point, WHY are you here?
下午好
Good afternoon
我在尋找博士
Im looking for the Doctor
唔 很明顯你找對地方了
Well youve certainly come to the right place
好!很好!
Good! Right!
那麼 你倆是誰?
Well, who are you boys?
哦當然!你倆是他的旅伴?
Oh, of course! Are you his companions?
他的旅伴?
His companions?
他們總是越來越年輕了!
They get younger all the time!
那麼 你們如果能指給我博士大概的方向的話
Well, if you could point me in the general direction of the Doctor
SONIC SCREWDRIVER WHIRRS
BOTH SONIC SCREWDRIVERS WHIRR
有沒有搞錯?
Really?
恩
Yeah
說真的 你們都是我?你倆都是?
ReallyYoure me? Both of you?
對 即便那個也是?
Yep Even that one?
是啊!
Yes!
你們是未來的我
Youre my future selves
對!對!
Yes! Yes!
我是遇上中年危機了麼?
Am I having a mid-life crisis?
你倆為什麼要這樣用你們的音速起子對著我?
Why are you pointing your screwdrivers like that?
它們是科學儀器 不是滋水槍
Theyre scientific instruments,not water pistols
就好像你們撞到鬼了!
Look like youve seen a ghost!
我還是喜歡時髦沙啞的腔調 很能讓人信服
Still loving the posh, gravelly thing Its very convincing
你還真敢說 Dick Van Dyke
（Dick Van Dyke在Mary Poppins裡的Cockney口音很糟糕 經常被吐槽）
Brave words, Dick Van Dyke
把他們圍起來!
Encircle them!
你們誰是博士
Which of you is the Doctor?
英格蘭的女王被人下蠱了 我要博士的首級
The Queen of England is bewitchedI would have the Doctors head
唔 這可是你的幸運日了
Well, this has all the makings of your lucky day
我想現在這裡有三個他
I think theres three of them now
-我想我們現在得聽聽他們說什麼 -之前已有先例
Clara:I think we must hear them now KATE: Theres a precedent for that
那是啥?
What is that?
哦 又指來指去了 它們是音速起子!
Oh, the pointing again Theyre screwdrivers!
你們準備幹嘛來著?組一個櫃子把他們裝起來嗎?
What are you going to do, assemble a cabinet at them(?)
那東西那是什麼蠱術?
That thing what witchcraft is it?
哦 對!
Ah, yes!
既然你提到它了 那確實是個蠱術 對 對 沒錯
Now that you mention it,that is witchcraft, yes, yes, yes
詭異古怪的蠱術 你好 有沒有人啊 抱歉 你好!
Witchy-witchcraft Hello? Hello in there? Excuse me Hello!
我是在和井裡的女巫說話嗎?
Am I talking to the wicked witch of the well?
他指的是你
He means you
為什麼我是女巫
Why am I the witch?
Clara 在嗎?
Clara? Hello?
Clara 嗨 你好啊
Clara, hi, hello
你好啊 你介意告訴這些囉囉嗦嗦的凡人
Hello Would you mind telling these prattling mortals
讓他們自行散退嗎
to get themselves begone?
按他說的做
Whathe said
恩 加多點語氣色彩嘛
Yes, tiny bit more colour
好
Right
哆哆嗦嗦的凡人們 快走開
Prattling mortals,off you pop,
不然我就把你們全都變成小青蛙
or Ill turn you all into frogs
哦 青蛙 真棒 你也聽到她說了
Oh, frogs, nice You heard her
博士 發生什麼了
Doctor, whats going on?
額 這可是個時空糾結的難題
Its a timey-wimey thing
時空神馬? 時空糾結?
Timeywhat? Timey-wimey?
完全不知道他是從哪兒學的
Ive no idea where he picks that stuff up
女王!
SOLDIERS: The Queen!
你們看上去沒跪下的意思 多麼勇敢啊
You dont seem to be kneeling How tremendously brave of you
你是哪一個?另外那個呢?噁心
Which one are you? What happened to the other one? Indisposed
女王萬歲!女王萬歲!
Long live the Queen!SOLDIERS: Long live the Queen!
逮捕他們 把他們帶去塔裡
Arrest these menTake them to the Tower
那可不是英格蘭女王 那是外星人複製的
That is not the Queen of England -thats an alien duplicate!
你們可以相信他說的話 因為他已經檢查過了 哦 閉嘴!
And you can take it from him, cos hes really checked Oh, shut up!
舌頭上有毒液囊泡 拜託 閉嘴!
Venom sacs in the tongue Seriously, stop it!
不 等等 塔!你是說倫敦塔麼?
No, hang on, the Tower!Did you say the Tower?
噢 真棒 超喜歡倫敦塔 唔 該八點上早餐啊
Ah, yes, brilliant, love the TowerBreakfast at eight, please
那會有Wifi嗎
Will there Wi-Fi?
你能說話不帶拍手嗎?
Are you capable of speaking without flapping your hands about?
能! 不!
Yes! No!
我要求被立刻關進倫敦塔
I demand to be incarcerated in the Tower immediately
-同時帶上我的倆個同謀 膠鞋小子還有老爺爺!-老爺爺?
with my co-conspirators, Sandshoes and Grandad! Grandad?
-它們可不是膠底鞋 -是的 它們就是!
Theyre not sandshoes Yes, they are!
閉嘴!倫敦塔可不能被輕易帶去
Silence! The tower is not to be taken lightly
很少人從那裡活著出來
Very few emerge again
-我的上帝 這人真聰明 跟著我 -我們去哪兒
Dear God, that mans cleverCome on! Where are we going?
我的辦公室 別名倫敦塔
My office Otherwise known as the Tower of London
哦 你們 滾進來
JAILER: Oi, you lot, get in there!
奧!
Ow!
TING!
我們三個在同一個牢房
Three of us in one cell -
如果我們不趕快走人的話一定會出現些奇怪的異常
thats going to cause some nasty anomalies if we dont get out soon
你在幹什麼
What are you doing?
帶我們出去!音速起子對那個不起作用 太原始了
Getting us out! The sonic wont work on that - its too primitive
我們該要求換一個更結實的門好讓我們溜走嗎
Shall we ask for a better quality of door so we can escape(?)
好 如今英格蘭的女王是個Zygon
OK, so the Queen of England is now a Zygon,
不過先別管這 為什麼我們會在一起
but never mind that, why are we all together?
為什麼我們都在這裡
Why are we all here?
額 我和尖下巴小子 我們很驚訝
Well, me and Chinny, we were surprised
但是是你來找我們
But you came looking for us -
你知道這一切都會發生 誰告訴你的
you knew it was going to happenWho told you?
喂! "尖下巴小子"?
Oi! "Chinny"?
是啊 你下巴是挺明顯的
Yeah, you do have a chin
大理石 花崗岩 各種不同的石頭
Marble, granitea lot of different stone,
但無一來自建築本身
but none of it from the fabric of the building
看上去似乎有人打爛了好多老雕像
Its like somebody smashed up a lot of old statues
有丟失的雕像嗎
Are there any missing?
不這麼認為
Dont think so
為什麼會有人這麼做
Why would anyone do that anyway?
我的意思是 我們是得保持開放的思維
I mean, I know were meant to keep an open mind,
但我們非要相信存在
but are we supposed to believe in creatures
能藏進油畫裡的
that can hide in oil paintings
並且對雕像有種奇怪的怨念的怪物麼?
and have some sort of a grudge against statues?
你還好麼?
You all right?
-我們得走了 就現在 這一分鐘內 -怎麼回事?
We have to go - right now,this minute Whats wrong?
來自畫裡的東西
The things from the paintings
我知道它們為什麼要打破雕像
I know why they smashed the statues
-為什麼 -因為它們得找個地方藏起來
Why? Because they needed somewhere to hide
GURGLING
SHE SCREAMS
哦!
Oh!
ALARM
博士會救我 博士會救我
The Doctor will save me,the Doctor will save me,
the Doctor will save me,the Doctor will save me,
博士會救我 博士會救我
the Doctor will save me,the Doctor will save me
對不起啊 我得要我的哮喘伴侶
Excuse me -Im going to need my inhaler
我真不喜歡攤上個有毛病的!
I so hate it when I get one with a defect!
哦 你在這裡有些很恐怖的回憶嘛
Oh, youve got some perfectly horrible memories in here,
不是麼
havent you?
嫉妒你那漂亮的姐姐
So jealous of your pretty sister
我可不會責怪你 我希望我複製的是她
I dont blame you,I wish Id copied HER
我也是
So do I!
哦 看在上帝份上
Oh, for goodness sake!
博士將會嘗試給我們發送一則消息
KATE: The Doctor will be trying to send us a message
我們在尋找一系列數碼
Were looking for a string of numerals
來自1550年 差不多那時候 第一優先
from around 1550, approximately -priority one
我需要訪問黑色檔案庫
Im going to need access to the Black Archive
黑色檔案庫
The Black Archive
這個星球上防衛等級最高的地方
Highest security rating on the planet
在每次輪班完每個工作人員都將被抹除記憶
The entire staff have their memories wiped at the end of every shift
房頂上有自動的記憶過濾器
Automated memory filters in the ceiling
鑰匙 夫人
Access, please Maam
是不是叫Aktins
Atkins, isnt it?
是的夫人 第一天在這裡上班
Yes, maam First day here
（悄悄話）在這裡差不多十年了
(Been here ten years)
鎖和鑰匙 挺原始的 不是麼
Lock and key - bit basic, isnt it?
這裡可不允許電子守衛系統
Cant afford electronic security down here -
在這裡得防備博士進來
got to keep the Doctor out
整座塔都是防TARDIS的
The whole of the Tower is TARDIS-proofed
-他可不會允許有這樣的收藏品 -但你卻讓我進來了
He really wouldnt approve of the collection But you let me in?
上次來過之後你擁有了我們這最高級的防衛等級
You have a top-level security rating from your last visit
抱歉 我的什麼
Sorry, my what?
抱歉 我們得監視已知的他的所有聯繫人
Apologies We have to screen all of his known associates -
我們可不能讓博士和TARDIS的情報
we cant have information about the Doctor and the TARDIS
落在壞人手裡
falling into the wrong hands
不然結果會是災難性的
The consequences could be disastrous
那是啥
What is that?
時間旅行
Time travel
時間渦流控制器 遵照Jack Harkness上校的遺囑
A vortex manipulator,bequeathed to the UNIT archive
在他死後贈與UNIT檔案館
by Captain Jack Harkness,on the occasion of his death
好吧 在他某一次死後
Well, one of them
-不可以有人知道我們擁有這些 即便是我們的同盟 -為什麼
No-one can know we have this, not even our allies Why not?
好好想想 美國人擁有重寫歷史的能力?
Think about it! Americans with the ability to rewrite history?
你也不是沒看過他們的電影
Youve seen their movies
好 這就是我們該如何解救博士
OK, so this is how were going to rescue the Doctor
我不知道是不是有足夠的能量進行往返旅行
Im not sure theres enough power for a two-way trip
無論如何 我們都不知道啟動密碼
In any event,we dont know the activation code
博士知道我們擁有這個
The Doctor knows we have this,
所以他老是把密碼藏著
so hes always kept the code from us
希望他改變想法了
PHONE RINGS Lets hope he changes his mind
是的
Yes
恩 既然你發現它了
Well, if youve found it,
把它拍下來並發到我的手機上
photograph it and send it to my phone
額 Kate 他們該在這裡嗎
Erm, Kate Should they be here?
他們為什麼要跟蹤我們
Why have they followed us?
哦 他們一定是提早把那些人類搞定了
Oh, theyve probably just finished disposing of the humans a bit early
人類?
The humans?
我的天啊 我入戲太深了 不是麼
Dear me! I really do get into character, dont I?
地下藝術館已被封閉
The Under Gallery is secured
準備再處理多一個人類 我們得到那設備了
Prepare to dispose of one more human We have acquired the device
啟動密碼 對嗎
Activation code - right?
理論上 我可以啟動單獨的音波
In theory, I can trigger an isolated sonic shift
在分子間移動這樣門就會被分體
among the molecules,and the door should disintegrate
我們得從亞原子水平上計算出
Wed have to calculate the exact harmonic resonance
整個結構的准群諧振頻率
of the entire structure down to a sub-atomic level
即便是音速起子也得耗上好幾年
Even the sonic would take years
不 不 音速起子得耗上好幾個世紀
No, no The sonic would take centuries
哦 那我們還是馬上開始的好
Oh, we might at all get started
麻煩告訴我那什麼"時間糾結"
Help to pass the "timey-wimey"
你非得像個小孩那樣說話嗎
Do you have to talk like children?
是什麼令你對成為大人那麼羞恥
What is it that makes you so ashamed of being a grown-up?
哦 你倆看我的方式 發生什麼了
Oh, the way you both look at me What is that?
我在嘗試找一個比"恐懼"更好的形容詞
Im trying to think of a better word than "dread"
那對於你來說一定才發生不久
It must be really recent for you
不久?
Recent?
時間大戰 最後那天 你殺了所有人的那天
The Time War, the last day The day you killed them all
-我們殺了所有人的那天 -一回事
The day WE killed them all Same thing
對於他們來說只是一段歷史 一切已被決定
Its history for them All decided
他們以為他們的未來是真實的 他們不知道
They think their future is real -they dont know
一切取決於你
its still up to you
我不跟人並不談論這事
I dont talk about it
你沒在跟人談論它 這裡沒別人 繼續 問他們
Youre not talking about it Theres no-one else here Go on Ask them
問他們你要知道的答案
Ask them what you need to know
你數過嗎?
Did you ever count?
數什麼?
Count what?
那天 Gallifrey上有多少個孩子
How many children there were on Gallifrey that day
我完全沒有概念
I have absolutely no idea
你現在多少歲了
How old are you now?
額 我不知道 我迷失方向了
AhI dont know, I lose track
我想我1200歲 除非我在撒謊
Twelve hundred and something,I think, unless Im lying
我不記得我是不是在對年齡撒謊 這就是我有多老
I cant remember if Im lying about my age - thats how old I am
比我老400歲
400 years older than me
在這麼長一段時間 你竟然沒有好奇過到底有多少個人?
And in all that time, youve never even wondered how many there were?
你竟然從沒數過?
You never once counted?
告訴我
Tell me
這有什麼意義
what would be the point?
24.7億
247 billion
你的確數過！
You DID count!
你忘記了
You forgot?
400年 400年你就都忘了?
400 years? Is that all it takes?
我繼續前進了
I moved on
向哪裡前進?! 如果你能忘記這種事 你現在在哪裡?
Where?! Where can you be now that you can forget something like that?
劇透 不
Spoilers No
不不不 就這一次 我希望知道我要往何處去
No, no, no For once, I would like to know where Im going
不 你絕對不會想知道
No You really wouldnt
我不知道你們是誰 你們倆
I dont know who you are either of you
我完全沒概念
I havent got the faintest idea
他們就是你
Theyre you
如果你毀滅Gallifrey的話 他們就是你要變成的人
Theyre what you become if you destroy Gallifrey
一直後悔的人
The man who regrets
與忘記一切的人
and the man who forgets
時間之匣就要開啟
The moment is coming
而時間之匣就是我 你需要做出決定
The Moment is me,you have to decide
不
No
No?
就是不
Just no!
HE LAUGHS
有什麼好笑的 我錯過了什麼有趣的事
Is something funny?Did I miss a funny thing?
對不起 只是我突然想起
Sorry It just occurred to me
我獨處的時候就是這樣
This is what Im like when Im alone
它們是同一把起子
Its the same screwdriver
同樣的軟件 不一樣的外殼
Same software different case
400年!
400 years!
抱歉
Im sorry?
在軟件層面上它們是一樣的 不是嗎
At a software level, theyre all the same device, arent they?
同樣的軟件 不同的外殼
Same software, different case
恩 所以
Yeah So?
所以 對於音速起子來說 它需要幾個世紀去計算
So, it would take centuries for the screwdriver to calculate
如何令這扇門解體 掃瞄這門
how to disintegrate the door Scanning the door,
把計算過程作為子程序
implanting the calculation as a permanent subroutine
永久植入軟件結構
in the software architecture
即使你們真的是我的話
and if you really are me,
就憑那沙灘鞋和奇怪的領結
with your sandshoes and your dicky bow,
音速起子也還是屬於我的
and that screwdriver is still mine
那麼計算過程應該還在繼續
that calculation is still going on
恩 還在進行
Yeah Still going
計算已完成
Calculation complete
同樣的軟件 不同的外殼
Same software Different face
額 400年濃縮在4秒鐘 我們或許有分歧
Eh, 400 years in four seconds We may have our differences,
在這情況下確實有點囧
which is frankly odd in the circumstances,
但我得告訴你們 娃娃們 我們太聰明了!
but I tell you what, boys, we are incredibly clever!
你是怎麼做到的
How did you that?
它都沒鎖 好不
It wasnt locked Right
所以他們都是你 對吧
So theyre both you, then, yeah?
對 你之前都見過他們了 還記得嗎
Yes Youve met them before,dont you remember?
一點啦 不錯的西裝
A bit Nice suit!
多謝
Thanks
等等
Hang on
三個你們在同一個牢房 但你們沒有一個想過嘗試一下開門
Three of you in one cell, and none of you thought to try the door
它本應鎖起來的啊
It should have been locked
對 沒錯 為什麼它沒被鎖起來
Yes, exactly! Why wasnt it locked?
因為我很想看看為了逃走你們會做些什麼
Because I was fascinated to see what you would do upon escaping
我知道你還比較喜歡這個世界
I understand youre rather fond of this world
是時候讓你看看會發生些什麼了
Its time I think you saw whats going to happen to it
Kate 哦天啊 你還沒死
Kate? Oh, goodness,youre not actually dead
哦 這還真是個大新聞
Oh, thats tremendous news!
那些怪物 他們把自己複製成我們
Those creatures,they turn themselves into copies
他們需要讓原型存活下來 更新他們的形象
And they need to keep the original alive, refresh the image,
可以這麼說
so to speak
他們去哪了
Wherewhere did they go?
我不知道 哦 等等 恩 我知道了 倫敦塔
I dont know Ooh, hang on -yes, I do The Tower
如果那些怪物進去了黑色檔案庫的話
If those creatures have got access to the Black Archive,
我們或許就要失去對這個星球的控制了
we may just have lost control of the planet
Zygon失去了他們的世界
The Zygons lost their own world
他們的母星在時間之戰的最初幾天消亡於烈火之中
It burned in the first days of the Time War
他們需要一個新的家園
A new home is required
所以他們想佔用這個
So they want this one?
還沒 太過原始了
Not yet Far too primitive
Zygon已經習慣了一定的舒適程度
Zygons are used to a certain level of comfort
指令官
Commander
為什麼這些怪物會在這裡
why are these creatures here?
因為我讓他們在這裡
Because I say they should be
是時候你倆也被傳送進去了
It is time you too were translated
觀察這一切
Observe this
我想你會覺得這很神奇
I believe you will find it fascinating
就是他 那就是在畫裡的Zygron
Thats him! Thats the Zygon in the picture now
那不是副畫 那是個停滯立方體
THE OTHER DOCTOR: Its not a picture,its a Stasis Cube
時間領主的藝術
Time Lord art -
時間上的固定瞬間 裡面比外面大
frozen instants in time,bigger on the inside
但也能被部署為
but could be deployed as
延遲動畫 哦 這還真棒
Suspended animation Oh, thats very good
Zygon全都跑進了畫裡 等上幾個世紀
The Zygons all pop inside the pictures, wait a few centuries
直到這星球變得有趣了那麼一點 他們便從裡面出來
till the planets a bit more interesting, and then out they come
Clara 你明白嗎
You see, Clara,
它們就藏在地下藝術館的畫裡面 就像速食湯那樣
theyre stored in the paintings inthe Under Gallery, like Cup-a-Soups
只不過你要加的是時間（而不是水） 如果你能想像那畫面的話
Except you add time -if you can picture that
沒人能想像那畫面好麼 忘掉速食湯的事吧
Nobody could picture that Forget I said Cup-a-Soups
如今這世界變得值得征服了
And now the world is worth conquering
所以Zygons是從過去
So the Zygons are invading the future
入侵未來
from the past
沒錯!
Exactly!
知道為什麼我知道你是個贗品嗎?
And do you know why I know that youre a fake?
因為你這贗品也太差了
Because you're such a bad copy.
不光是你的氣味 或者這缺乏說服力的頭髮
It's not just the smell,or the unconvincing hair,
或者這一口爛牙，或者你的眼睛 它們靠的太近了
or the atrocious teeth, or the eyes just a bit too close together,
還有口臭 能熏倒一匹馬
or the breath that could stun a horse
是因為我的伊麗莎白 真正的伊麗莎白
it's because my Elizabeth,the real Elizabeth,
絕對不會蠢到自己揭露她的計劃
would never be stupid enough to reveal her own plan.
說真的 你為什麼這麼做?
Honestly, why would you do that?
因為這不是我的計劃
Because it's not my plan,
而我是真正的伊麗莎白
and I AM the real Elizabeth.
啊好 那 我們往回倒一點
OK. So...backtracking a moment,
給我之前的評論加一點上下文
just to lend some context to my earlier remarks...
我那雙胞胎在森林裡死了
My twin is dead in the forest.
我習慣於採取警戒措施
I am accustomed to taking precautions.
這些Zygon怪物一點也沒想到是我
These Zygon creatures never even considered that it was me
而不是他們的指揮官 活了下來
who survived,rather than their own commander.
狂妄是他們種族的特點
The arrogance that typifies their kind.
Zygons?
天啊!你真的殺了一個？
Men!
And you actually killed one of them?
我也許擁有一個弱小脆弱女人的身軀
I may have the body of a weak and feeble woman,
但那個時候 那個Zygon也是如此
我的王國危在旦夕
博士 我能信賴你嗎?
這樣的話 我就需要我的TARDIS了
已經到手了 哈!
但首先 吾愛，你有個承諾要守住！
我現在宣佈你們為…丈夫和妻子
你可以吻新娘了
未來有很多這種事情嗎？
從現在開始 是的
上帝保佑 我的愛
我馬上就回來
喔!
好的 接下來 回到未來
看你把這裡折騰的!
啊 這是他的邋遢階段 慢慢會好的
你別聽他們的!
噢! 界面故障了
我們三個來自不同的時間 它在嘗試修理整合
嘿 看 這些圓圓的東西
我超愛這些圓圓的東西
不知道
哦 天 摩擦相反控制器
哈!這兒呢!穩定下來了
哦 你重新裝修過了！
我不喜歡
哦? 噢 對 哦
你從來都不! 聽著 我們要去國立美術館 Zyong們就在那下面
不 去UNIT總部 他們尾隨我們到了黑色檔案館
好吧 所以你們聽說過那個
這裡的儀器超凡脫俗
有一半的東西人類都不知道是用來幹什麼的
我們可以在一天內就征服他們的世界
在對於複製品的選擇上
我們非常幸運
如果我是人類，我會說這就像聖誕節一樣
不 很抱歉你不會的 我們沒有武器 你可以放鬆
我們有武器 你沒法放鬆
鎖上門
很抱歉我們不可以被打擾到
你不介意我坐的舒服點吧?
你不介意我也坐的舒服點吧?
你會意識到有議定條款保護著這個地方的
-Osgood -倘若有外星人入侵的事件發生
因為這屋裡的所有的東西都被視為極端危險
-它會自我銷毀 在 -五分鐘之內
20英尺之下有個核彈頭對著我們
你坐的還舒服嗎?
你要毀滅倫敦?
來保護世界? 是的 我會
你在虛張聲勢
你真的這麼覺得?
你的記憶中會有一個人名叫
Brigadier Alistair Gordon Lethbridge-Stewart.
Alistair Gordon Lethbridge-Stewart旅長
我是他的女兒
"科學引導" Kate 這是你的本意嗎?
"Science leads," Kate. Is that what you meant?
"這是你父親的本意嗎?"
博士?
一個我送給你父親的禮物 呼叫TARDIS的直通熱線
我知道黑色檔案館的事情 我也知道安保條款的事情
Kate 拜託
請不要告訴我你要做些超級愚蠢的事情
-很抱歉 博士 -關掉它
你以後會更抱歉
Not as sorry as you will be.
這不是你能夠背負一生的決定
Kate! 我們要把TARDIS開過來 為什麼我們不能著陸
我說了 關掉它!
不 Kate 拜託，聽我說...
倫敦塔 完全防TARDIS
他們怎麼做到的?
外星科技加上人類的愚蠢
相信我 它是無法戰勝的
我們不需要著陸
不 我們需要 有一點點需要 試著跟上節奏
不 我們不需要 我們不需要 還有別的辦法
No, we don't. We don't.There is another way.
速食湯!
什麼速食湯!
發生什麼了?
展示給你看更方便點
McGillop.
看看你的手機 確定下你在和誰講話
但這不可能 我剛剛才
你剛剛在和我說話 我知道
我是個時間旅行者 自己琢磨去吧
我需要你把Gallifrey的隕落這幅畫送到黑色檔案館
明白?
但我為什麼要帶過去?
你的一句話就可以取消倒計時
確實
它根據你的聲紋定調
只有我的
不再是這樣了 取消爆炸!
撤回命令!
我們只有同意才能生存
很不幸 我們只能同意死亡
求你 博士 請救救我們
請救救我們 請救救我們
請救救我們
消滅!
你好
我是博士
抱歉Dalek來搗亂了
還有這些臭顯擺
Kate Lethbridge-Stewart 你都幹了些什麼好事?
只有我親自下令倒計時才能停止
你什麼也做不了
除非讓你們兩個都同意停止
你們三個也阻止不了我
你會殺掉幾百萬人的
拯救了幾十億 這樣的計算你做過幾次?
一次
把我變成了現在這樣的人
我甚至都不再確定這個人是誰
你告訴自己這是正義的 但它是個謊言
因為我那天做的事情是錯誤的 完全錯誤
正是因為我當時做錯了
我現在要讓你…做對它
怎麼做?
接下來的任何一秒 你要停止那個倒計時
你們兩個 一起
然後你去談判出一個最完美的協議
防護措施全面啟動 對雙方都公平
完美談判的訣竅就是
不知道自己的立場是哪一方
那麼 直到我們決定放你走
接下來的幾個小時裡
這房間裡將沒有一個人能記得自己到底是人類
還是Zygon
..
Or Zygon.
哎呦呦個菊花開燦爛的開!
取消爆炸!
我們的和平年代
很好玩 對吧?
如果我是個Zygon 那我的衣服也一定是Zygon
那麼 如果我丟了一隻鞋或者別的什麼的怎麼辦?
哦!
Oh!
你好
你好 我叫Clara
我們還沒見過面
我期待著
有問題嗎?
博士 我的那個
我的那個博士
他常常說起那天
他毀滅時間領主來終止戰爭的那天
有人會
你不會
因為你還沒去做 這件事仍然在你的未來
你對自己很肯定
他很後悔 我每天都能從他的眼睛裡讀到愧疚
他願意做任何事情來改變
包括拯救這些所有人
你覺得他的愧疚拯救了多少個世界？
放眼看看 - 人類和Zygon們和平的相處在一起
你怎麼知道?
你的眼睛
你年輕很多
深思熟慮之下
我是該成長起來了
..
it's time I grew up.
我需要見識的都見過了
這一刻已經到來
我準備好了
我知道你準備好了
誰在那?
你想要一個大紅按鈕
一聲巨響  再也沒有時間領主
再也沒有Dalek
你確定嗎?
我當時來這的時候非常確定
沒有別的方法
你見過了你將會成為的人
那些人
非同尋常
他們曾經是你
不
No.
他們是博士
They were the Doctor.
而你也是博士
You're the Doctor too.
不
No.
偉大的人鍛造於烈火之中
Great men are forged in fire.
點燃這個火焰是小人物的榮幸...
It is the privilege of lesser men to light the flame...
無論代價是什麼..
..whatever the cost.
（孩子的笑聲）
CHILDREN LAUGH
你知道TARDIS發出的聲音吧？
You know the sound the TARDIS makes?
那個呼哧作響的...低哼聲
That wheezing...groaning.
那個聲音給所到之處都帶去了希望
That sound brings hope wherever it goes.
是的 是的 我希望它帶到了
Yes. Yes, I like to think it does.
給每一個聽到它的人 博士
To anyone who hears it, Doctor.
任何人 無論多麼的迷失...
Anyone, however lost...
..甚至是你!
..even you!
我告訴過你 他還沒有做過
I told you - he hasn't done it yet.
你們全都給我走開
Go away now, all of you.
這是我的事情
This is for me.
這些事情應該被時間鎖住 我們根本不應該在這裡
These events should be time locked - we shouldn't even be here.
所以有什麼東西讓我們穿過來了
So something let us through.
你們幾個聰明的男孩！
You clever boys!
回去
Go back.
回去你們自己的生活
Go back to your lives.
去成為那個我無法成為的博士
Go and be the Doctor that I could never be.
讓這變得有意義
Make it worthwhile.
這麼多年 把你埋藏在我的記憶裡
All those years, burying you in my memory.
假裝你不存在
Pretending you didn't exist.
把你當做秘密 甚至對我自己也是
Keeping you a secret, even from myself.
裝作你不是博士
Pretending you weren't the Doctor,
儘管你比任何人都適合博士這個身份
when you were the Doctor more than anybody else.
在事情本不可能做對的那天 你是博士
You were the Doctor on the day it wasn't possible to get it right.
但這一次...
But this time...
..你不需要獨自面對
..You don't have to do it alone.
謝謝你
Thank you.
我們今天所做的事不是出自恐懼或怨恨
What we do today is not out of fear or hatred.
我們這樣做是因為別無它法
It is done because there is no other way.
我們這樣做是為了我們沒能拯救的那些生命
And it is done in the name of the many lives we are failing to save.
怎麼了?
What?
喂 到底怎麼了?
What is it, what?
沒什麼… 沒事
Nothing... No.
是什麼 告訴我！
It's something. Tell me!
你告訴我你毀滅了你的種族 我只是...
You told me you wiped out your own people. I just...
我無法想像你做了這種事 僅此而已
I never pictured you doing it, that's all.
仔細看清楚
Take a closer look.
發生什麼事情了?
CLARA: What's happening?
沒事  這是個投影
Nothing - it's a projection.
圍繞你的是一個現實
ROSE: It's a reality around you.
這就是你要燒死的人?
These are the people you're going to burn?
沒有什麼我們可以做的了
There isn't anything we can do.
他說的對
He's right.
沒有別的方法 從來都沒有
There isn't another way, there never was.
要麼我就毀滅掉自己的種族 要麼我就讓整個宇宙灰飛煙滅
Either I destroy my own people or let the universe burn.
看看你們...
Look at you...
..你們三個
..the three of you.
戰士 英雄
The warrior. The hero.
還有你
And you.
我是什麼？
And what am I?
你真的忘記了嗎?
Have you really forgotten?
是的 也許是的
Yes. Maybe, yes.
我們已經有了足夠多的戰士
We've got enough warriors -
隨便一個老糊塗都可以當英雄
any old idiot can be hero.
那我能做什麼？
Then what do I do?
做你常做的
What you've always done.
做個博士!
Be a doctor!
你告訴過我你選擇的這個名字是一個承諾
You told me the name you chose was a promise.
那承諾是什麼？
What was the promise?
永不摧殘他人 也不怯懦怕事
Never cruel or cowardly.
永不放棄
Never give up,
永不屈服
never give in.
你不是真的建議我們改變我們自己的歷史吧?
You're not actually suggesting that we change our own personal history?
我們一直在改變歷史
We change history all the time.
我在建議一些更糟糕的事情
I'm suggesting something far worse.
到底是什麼？
What, exactly?
先生們 我用了400年的時間來思考這個
Gentleman, I have had 400 years to think about this.
我改變主意了
I've changed my mind.
那裡還是會有數以百計的Dalek進行著攻擊
There's still a billion billion Daleks up there, attacking.
是的 會有 會有
Yeah, there is, there is.
但有些事情是那數以百計的Dalek不知道的
But there's something those billion billion Daleks don't know.
因為如果他們知道 他們應該就會叫援軍了
Cos if they did, they'd probably send for reinforcements.
什麼  他們不知道什麼?
What, what don't they know?
這一次 這裡有我們三個人
This time, there's three of us.
哦!
Oh!
哦!哦 是的 很好!
Oh! Oh, yes, that is good!
太棒了!
That is brilliant!
哦 哦 哦! 我知道了 那太-太棒了!
Oh, oh, oh! I'm getting that too - that is brilliant!
哈 哈 哈! 我已經想了好幾個世紀了!
Ha-ha-ha! I've been thinking about it for centuries!
她不是隨便給我看了某一個未來
She didn't just show me any old future -
她給我看的是正我需要看見的那個未來!
she showed me exactly the future I needed to see!
現在你明白了
Now you're getting it.
誒? 誰給你看的?
Eh? Who did?
哦 惡狼女孩 我真該親親你
Oh, Bad Wolf Girl, I could kiss you.
沒錯 這肯定會發生的
Yep, that's going to happen!
對不起 你剛剛是不是說 "惡狼"?
Sorry, did you say, "Bad Wolf"?
所以我們要怎麼做?
So what are we doing?
計劃是什麼?
What's the plan?
Dalek艦隊正包圍Gallifrey 持續不斷向它開火
The Dalek fleets are surrounding Gallifrey, firing on it constantly.
天溝戰壕正在阻擋戰火 但如果整個星球…
The Sky Trench is holding, but what if the whole planet...
就這麼消失了? 不過是一點小小的要求
just disappeared? Tiny bit of an ask.
Dalek的炮火就會射向他們自己
The Daleks would be firing on each other -
他們就會被自己的火力消滅掉
they'd destroy themselves in their own crossfire.
Gallifrey將會消失 Dalek將被摧毀
Gallifrey would be gone, the Daleks would be destroyed,
而在宇宙中其他人看來
and it would look to the rest of the universe
好像是他們彼此摧毀殲滅了對方
as if they'd annihilated each other.
但Gallifrey會在哪兒呢? 完全被凍住!
But where would Gallifrey be? Frozen!
凍結在一個時間片段裡
Frozen in an instant of time,
安安全全藏起來
safe and hidden away.
沒錯!
Exactly!
像幅畫一樣
Like a painting.
又來了一個!
ANDROGAR: Another one!
你確定信息是從他那裡來的？
THE GENERAL: Are you sure the message is from him?
- 哦 是的!
- Oh, yes!
- 他為什麼要這麼做?
- Why would he do that?
那個瘋狂的蠢貨事到如今還要說什麼?
What's the mad fool talking about now?
喂 喂 Gallifrey最高指揮官
Hello, hello, Gallifrey High Command,
我是博士
this is the Doctor speaking.
喂 我也是博士 你能聽到我嗎?
Hello! Also the Doctor. Can you hear me?
還是博士 時刻準備著
Also the Doctor - standing ready.
天啊 三個他! 我最可怕的噩夢們一下子都出現了!
Dear God, three of them! All my worse nightmares at once!
將軍 我們有個計劃 我們在這個時候 要提出
'General, we have a plan. We should point out, at this moment,
一個非常可怕的計劃 而且幾乎完全不可能奏效
it is a fairly terrible plan. And almost certainly won't work.
我覺得 "非常可怕" 這個用詞很巧妙
I was happy with "fairly terrible".
不好意思 一想出神就說出來了
Sorry, just thinking out loud.
我們現在正駕駛著3部TARDIS進入你們的低空大氣層
We're flying our three TARDISes into your lower atmosphere.
我們正保持著相等間距環繞著星球
We're positioned at equidistant intervals round the globe.
"相等間距" 聽上去真成熟!
"Equidistant" - so grown-up!
我們正準備要這麼做
We're just about ready to do it.
準備做什麼?
THE GENERAL: 'Ready to do what?'
我們要凍在Gallifrey
We're going to freeze Gallifrey.
對不起我沒聽清 你們要什麼?
I'm sorry, what?
我們將用我們的TARDIS
Using our TARDISes,
把Gallifrey凍結在一個時間點
we're going to freeze Gallifrey in a single moment in time.
你知道 就像那些停滯立方體一樣
'You know, like those Stasis Cubes?'
一個存在於平行口袋宇宙中的時間點
A single moment in time held in a parallel pocket universe.
只不過我們現在要對整個星球這樣做
Except we're going to do it to a whole planet.
還有星球上所有人
And all the people on it.
什麼? 就算這是可能的
What? Even if that were possible,
儘管這事實上並不可能 你們為什麼要這麼做?
'which it isn't, why would you do such a thing?'
因為另一個選擇是燃燒整個星球 我過去看到了
Because the alternative is burning. And I've seen that.
而且我永遠不想再看一次
And I never want to see it again.
我們會迷失在另一個宇宙中...
We'd be lost in another universe...
..凍結在一個時間點裡
..frozen in a single moment.
我們會一無所有
We'd have nothing.
你們會有希望
You would have hope.
而現在 這正是你們所沒有的
And right now, that is exactly what you don't have.
一派胡言 只是運算就要
It's delusional. The calculations alone
花上...幾百年的時間
would take...hundreds of years.
哦 好幾百年
Oh, hundreds and hundreds.
但別擔心
But don't worry -
我很久之前就開始了!
I started a very long time ago!
呼叫Gallifrey戰爭議會 這裡是博士
Calling the War Council of Gallifrey, this is the Doctor.
你應該說 我這輩子都在幹這個!
You might say, I've been doing this all my lives!
祝你好運! 預備
Good luck! Stand by.
準備好了嗎？開始運算
Ready? Commencing calculations.
馬上就好
Soon be there.
跨過分割宇宙的界限
'Across the boundaries that divide one universe from another.
只要鎖住他的坐標
Just got to lock on to his coordinates.
然後我下一個小花招...!
And for my next trick...!
我都不知道自己什麼時候這麼走運過! 全部12個!
I didn't know when I was well off! All 12 of them!
不，長官...
ANDROGAR: No, sir...
全部13個!
..all 13!
長官! Dalek察覺到了
Sir! The Daleks know that something is happening.
他們加強火力了
They're increasing their fire power.
快做 博士
Do it, Doctor.
現在就做
Just do it.
（金屬敲擊聲）
METALLIC THRUMMING
現在!
Do it!
好的
OK.
先生們… 我們準備好了
Gentleman...we're ready.
Geronimo...!
Allons-y!
哦 看在上帝的份上!
Oh, for God's sake!
Gallifrey屹立不倒!
Gallifrey stands!
我覺得我們永遠不會知道我們到底有沒有成功
I don't suppose we'll ever know if we actually succeeded.
但就算是最糟糕的情況
But at worst,
我們也是沒做成正確的事情
we failed doing the right thing,
而不是做成了錯誤的事情
as opposed to succeeding in doing the wrong.
生命和靈魂 你們幾個!
Life and soul, you are
這到底應該叫什麼?
What is it actually called?
這個嘛 有點爭論
Well, there's some debate.
要麼」終結」
Either No More
要麼就"Gallifrey的隕落」
or Gallifrey Falls.
一點也不鼓舞人心
Not very encouraging.
它是怎麼變成這樣的?
How did it get here?
不知道
No idea.
總是有一些我們不知道的事情 不是嗎?
There's always something we don't know, isn't there?
但願如此
One should certainly hope so.
好了 先生們...
Well, gentlemen...
這是我的榮耀
it has been an honour...
和幸運
and a privilege.
我也是 博士
Likewise. Doctor.
若我成長為有你一半好的人
And if I grow to be half the man
Clara Oswald
that you are, Clara Oswald,
我就會非常滿足了
I shall be happy indeed.
這就對了 要胸懷大志!
That's right - aim high!
我不會記住這些的 對嗎?
I won't remember this, will I?
時間流沒法同步
The time streams are out of sync.
不 你記不住的
You can't retain it, no.
所以我也不會記得我曾拯救過Gallifrey
So I won't remember that I tried to save Gallifrey,
而不是燒掉了它
rather than burn it.
我不得不接受這個
I'll have to live with that.
但現在
But for now,
這一刻...
for this moment...
我再一次成為了博士
..I am the Doctor again.
謝謝你
Thank you.
哪個是我的?!
Which one is mine?!
哈!
Ha!
（金屬敲擊聲）
METALLIC THRUMMING
哦 是的...
Oh, yes...
沒錯 這就對了…
Course, suppose it makes sense...
變瘦點
Wearing a bit thin.
我希望這次耳朵別那麼顯眼了
I hope the ears are bit less conspicuous this time.
反正我不會記得 所以你最好告訴我
I won't remember either, so you might as well tell me.
告訴你什麼?
Tell you what?
那個我們會將會去但你卻不想提起的地方
Where it is we're going that you don't want to talk about.
我看到了Trenzalore...
I saw Trenzalore...
我們被埋葬的地方
where we're buried.
我們同數以百萬的人在戰爭中死去
We die in battle among millions.
這不應該發生的
That's not how it's supposed to be.
故事就是這麼結束的  我們什麼也做不了
That's how the story ends - nothing we can do about it.
Trenzalore是你要去的地方
Trenzalore is where you're going.
哦 永遠別說什麼也做不了
Oh, never say nothing.
無論如何...
Anyway...
知道我的未來在可靠的人手裡是個好消息
good to know my future is in safe hands.
握住別放 Clara
Keep a tight hold on it, Clara.
嗯! 搞定!
Mm! On it!
Trenzalore.
我們需要一個新的目的地 因為...
We need a new destination, because...
..我不想去那兒
..I don't want to go.
（金屬敲擊聲）
METALLIC THRUMMING
他總是這麼說
He always says that.
需要和你的畫單獨待會嗎?
Need a moment alone with your painting?
你怎麼知道的? 那對憂傷的大眼睛 啊
How did you know? Those big, sad eyes. Ah.
我一直都知道
I always know.
哦 對了 有個老人在找你
Oh, by the way, there was an old man looking for you.
我覺得是館長
I think it was the curator.
我可以當館長
I could be a curator.
我可以非常擅長策展
I'd be great at curating.
我可以是個…非常偉大的館長
I'd be...the great curator.
我可以現在退休然後做這些
I could retire and do that.
我可以退休了然後做這裡的館長
I could retire and be the curator of this place.
我每張臉都不會忘記
I never forget a face.
我知道你不會 然後隨著時間推移
I know you don't, and in years to come,
你會發現自己在重訪一些面孔
you might find yourself revisiting a few
但就只是…最喜歡的那幾張老面孔 呃?
but just...the old favourites, eh?
我覺得你對這幅畫很好奇
You were curious about this painting, I think.
我是在一個非同尋常的情況下得到它的
I acquired it in remarkable circumstances.
你覺得這幅畫的標題怎麼樣?
What do you make of the title?
哪個標題? 它有兩個
Which title? There's two.
終結
No More...
還是Gallifrey的隕落?
..or Gallifrey Falls?
哦 你看 這就是大家都弄錯的地方
Oh, you see, that's where everybody's wrong.
這是同一個標題
It's all one title.
終結Gallifrey的隕落
Gallifrey Falls No More.
現在 你覺得這是什麼意思 嗯?
Now, what would you think that means, eh?
就是Gallifrey沒有隕落
That Gallifrey didn't fall.
成功了 它仍然在那裡
It worked. It's still out there.
我只是一個卑微的館長 我肯定不會知道
I'm only a humble curator - I'm sure I wouldn't know.
- 那它在哪兒呢?
- 到底在哪兒呢?
- Then where is it?
- Where is it indeed?
消失了  噓!  也許吧
Lost - shh! - perhaps.
你知道 東西經常會不見的
Things do get lost, you know.
現在 希望你允許我離開一下
Now you must excuse me.
哦...
Oh...
你有很多事情要做
you have a lot to do.
是嗎? 嗯 這是我現在要做的事情嗎?
Do I? Mm. Is that what I'm supposed to do now?
- 去找Gallifrey?
- 哦 這完全取決於你 你的選擇
- Go looking for Gallifrey?
- Oh, it's entirely up to you. Your choice.
我只能告訴你我會做什麼
I can only tell you what I would do,
如果我是你...
if I were you...
哦...!如果我是你的話…
Oh...! If I were you...
也許我曾經是你 當然
Perhaps I WAS you, of course.
又或者...
Or perhaps...
你是我
you are me.
耶! 恭喜恭喜
Yeah! Congratulations.
非常感謝
Thank you very much.
或許不管誰是誰都無所謂
Or perhaps it doesn't matter either way.
誰知道呢?
Who knows?
究竟是誰…知道呢?
Who...knows?
Clara有時問我會不會做夢
Clara sometimes asks me if I dream.
"我當然會做夢" 我告訴她
"Course I dream," I tell her.
每個人都會做夢
"Everybody dreams.
但你都夢到些什麼 她問
' "But what do you dream about?" she'll ask.
和每個人夢到的一樣 我告訴她
"The same thing everybody dreams about," I tell her.
我夢到我要去的地方
"I dream about where I'm going."
她總是因為這個哈哈大笑
'She always laughs at that.
但你哪裡都不去 你只是在亂晃
"But you're not going anywhere - you're just wandering about."
不是這樣的 以後都不會了
'That's not true. Not any more.
我有了一個新的目的地
'I have a new destination.
我的旅途和你的一樣 和所有人的都一樣
'My journey is the same as yours, the same as anyone's.
它花費了我這麼多年 這麼多次轉生
'It's taken me so many years, so many lifetimes,
但我終於我要去哪裡了
'but at last I know where I'm going,
我一直試圖去那個的地方
'where I've always been going.
我那很遠很遠的...家
Home...the long way round.